<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mourner comforted an epistle consolatory / written by Hugo Grotius to Monsieur Du Maurier the French embassadour at the Hague ; translated on a sad occasion by C.B.</title>
            <title>Epistola consolatoria ad Benjaminum Auberium Maurerium, Regis Christianissimi apud Foederatas Belgii Provincias legatum illustrissimum. English</title>
            <author>Grotius, Hugo, 1583-1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2114</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1086</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07933705</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07933705</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40523</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42228)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40523)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1207:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mourner comforted an epistle consolatory / written by Hugo Grotius to Monsieur Du Maurier the French embassadour at the Hague ; translated on a sad occasion by C.B.</title>
                  <title>Epistola consolatoria ad Benjaminum Auberium Maurerium, Regis Christianissimi apud Foederatas Belgii Provincias legatum illustrissimum. English</title>
                  <author>Grotius, Hugo, 1583-1645.</author>
                  <author>Barksdale, Clement, 1609-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for Edward Lee,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translated by Clement Barksdale.  Cf. Meulen, J. ter, Bibliographie des ʹecrits imprimʹes de Hugo Grotius, 1950, p. 617.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40523:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MOURNER COMFORTED. AN Epiſtle Conſolatory; WRITTEN BY <hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GO GROTI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> TO Monſieur <hi>DU MAURIER</hi> the French Embaſſadour at the HAGUE. <hi>Tranſlated on a ſad occaſion, by</hi> C.B.</p>
            <q>Melius ſe fert ſparſus Dolor.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A.M.</hi> for <hi>Edward Lee</hi> at the Turks Head in Fleetſtreet. 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:40523:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40523:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His had not ſeen the light, but that it may be uſefull to ſome of the Relatives of that excellent Lady, that could not go to her grave unobſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, nor without great attendance. Her departure may be compared to the diſappearing of ſome ſtar of the firſt magnitude. Or rather, a new ſtar is thereby added to the heavens. And there let her ſhine for ever. The uſe of this Epiſtolical Diſcourſe may alſo extend farther then my
<pb facs="tcp:40523:3"/>
firſt deſign. They that faint under any ſuch loſſe may take it for a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial: and they that fear any, may receive it for a preparative. This (upon ſome experience in himſelf) is the hope of the Tranſlator in the publication of it; and it is Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thoſe Honourable perſons, whom he will not preſume to name, untill by ſome more ample testimony he may publickly ſhew himſelf their faithful and humble ſervant,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>C.B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40523:3"/>
            <head>HUGO GROTIUS His Conſolatory Epiſtle to the French Embaſſador <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> MA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RIER,</hi> upon the Death of his Lady.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt, Illuſtrious Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am thus far indebted to my priſon, that the evils of other men come later to my knowledge; even your wound, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe I ſhould have known among the firſt, by reaſon of that friendſhip wherewith you have honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me, I now underſtand laſt of all, like unto thoſe things that come to paſs in the remoteſt parts of Europe. This will excuſe the ſlowneſſe of my duty, which yet beſide neceſſity hath reaſon enough to defend it. For thoſe conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations are wont to be more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which are then applied, when the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40523:4"/>
firſt ſtorm of ſorrow is paſt, and that pleaſure (if I may ſo ſpeak) of grieving is abated; when the minde now wearied with its diſeaſe begins to be willing to admit of remedies, and to ſuffer the touch of ſome helping hand. I know how you were affected with my calamity, and thence you may underſtand, I am not unſenſible of your ſorrow. Let us, if it pleaſe you, mingle together the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of our grief, that we may together ſeek for comforts, and when we have found them make uſe of them together. Neither am I ignorant, how little I, that am ſo deſtitute of all aids both to my minde and body, am able to bring unto this purpoſe, which is not already better and more effectually alledged and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the profeſſors of wiſdom or eloquence or piety, who have hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſet up their ſtandard againſt immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate mourning. But I am taught by my own experience, That can never be too much repeated which is never e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough remembred. We muſt ſcour and call back into uſe the Arms, which by length of time are grown ruſty. Beſides, the advices which are given in general words, as ſpoken unto all, are wont to paſs by with leſs obſervation: but when
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40523:4"/>
they are applied to our particular caſe, having no other mark to hit, they pierce and have a more ſtrong effect. At our firſt entrance upon this work, we muſt ſeriouſly conſider, whether the grief of the heart be in the number of thoſe things, over which our labour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry hath any power. For if neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily and naturally we do all grieve ſo much as the greatneſs of the occaſion, and the immutable frame of every ones minde requireth, it is eaſily underſtood all pains to the contrary is taken in vain. Nor doubt I but rude mindes ſurprized with ſome ſuch perſwaſion do ſometimes give up themſelves to the poſſeſſion of grief, as of a diſeaſe incurable. They feel ſad thoughts come into the minde unſent for, whence follows that preſſure of the heart contracting it ſelf, which we call <hi>maeror,</hi> and ſo without more ado they throw down their arms in deſpair of victory. But we, who beſides our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward experience (which alone rightly obſerved might ſuffice) have the helps of excellent arts, and the uſe of all lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and wiſe mens labours before us, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ignorant of the truth in this point, if we pleaſe but to rouſe our ſelves up, and draw forth what we have hid
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40523:5"/>
within us. The truth is this, Thoſe firſt appearances, and the ſuddain motions ariſing thence, which the wiſe compare to the twinklings of the eyes, are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our power; but to admit of thoſe appearances and let them without judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and diſcretion into the cloſet of the heart; or elſe to paſs a ſtrict examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon them, and weigh them in the ſcale of reaſon: alſo, to looſe the reigns to the affections, or to reſtrain them; this for the moſt part is within our pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. That ſorrow may be overcome, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelf teacheth us; for, if by no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means, it is at laſt conſumed by time. Art imitates Nature. The Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician obſerving any diſeaſe mitigated by naturall ſweat, endeavours to eaſe his patient ſick of the like diſeaſe by medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines that procure ſweating. The new Philoſophers, the Chymiſts, worthy of more praiſe and favour, if they did not corrupt the glory of their excellent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions by vainglorious promiſes, teach that the nature of metalls is ambulato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and by long continuance of time one is changed into another: and herein conſiſts their induſtry, to promote the endeavors of nature, and haſten that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect which will at length be produced.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40523:5"/>
Such is the office of right reaſon in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercoming ſorrow. Sorrow hath this good in it, above other evils, it bears not age. Other diſeaſes of the minde are nouriſhed, this is waſted by time. You may ſuppoſe it is a weak enemy, that cannot maintain it ſelf, and without any force oppoſed, fals of it ſelf. What na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture promiſeth at a longer day, reaſon repreſents and pays down in hand. Let us therefore, as it is the property of Art, follow the ſteps of nature. When by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and little the grief of minde depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, there is for the moſt part no change in the thing it ſelf, yea the incommodity that was, often becomes greater, as when he that hath loſt a friend or wife declines to old age, wherein he hath moſt need of helps. Whence then ariſes that calm in a minde ſo much troubled before? Truly hence, the appearance of the thing that cauſeth ſorrow is more ſeldom in the eye of the minde; it ſlides by, not ſticks, it touches, doth not preſs or pierce the minde, and at laſt it doth not ſo much as touch it. Conſider now whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther every one be not able ſpeedily to cure himſelf, and haſten his own enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſo great a good. Moſt of us not only ſuffer, but create our ſorrow,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40523:6"/>
whilſt we yield our ſelves to ſudden co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations; in mourning eſpecially, where the vexation flatters us under a ſhew of piety. Thoſe ſad thoughts we cheriſh carefully, and to our own hurt patronize, doing like them that ſeek for looking-glaſſes which repreſent bodies greater then they are. Surely, the will of man, that hath ſuch force to hurt himſelf, might do ſomewhat, if it pleaſed, for his own eaſe. That ſorrow is an enemy to us, we cannot deny. The leanneſſe of an exhauſted body, paleneſs of counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, dejection of minde (cauſes of grief for the moſt part more juſt then that for which we grieve) ſhew it to be an enemy. In the dealing with an enemy, what are we wont to do? If he be ſtrong and at the firſt onſet violent, whilſt your forces are not yet come together; the firſt caution is, to decline the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell: afterward, when you are aſſured and confident in your ſtrength, you ſhall march into the field and diſplay your co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours. Even ſo the appearance of your loſs being freſh, and your minde tender, it is beſt to bend your thoughts another way. None may do it more eaſily, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Sir, then you, who need not ſeek for employment, you have in your charge
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40523:6"/>
affairs of ſo great weight and labour, that they may very take up all your thoughts. The King whom you ſerve, the greateſt and moſt Chriſtian, the difficult times, the many and various buſineſſes of your Office, what elſe do they all ſay unto you, but; <hi>Attend your work, you are not at leaſure to be a Mourner.</hi> Moſt true is that old ſaying, <hi>The minde is prevalent, where you put it forth and uſe it.</hi> Certainly it is there to be uſed, where our labour may be to good purpoſe; that is, not in mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but in the ſervice of your King and Country. It is no more then ordinary common ſenſe which the Greek Poet hath adorned with elegant expreſſions to this effect;
<q>
                  <l>If ills were cured by our weeping eyes,</l>
                  <l>And tears could waſh away our miſeries;</l>
                  <l>Thy tears were worth gold: which I now muſt blame,</l>
                  <l>For weep, or weep not, evils are the ſame.</l>
               </q>
I know that, ſaid <hi>Solon,</hi> and I weep the more, becauſe I can do no good by weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This very fooliſh ſaying of ſo wiſe a man may be an example to us, how much ſorrow darkneth the judgement, that made <hi>Solon</hi> himſelf to ſpeak unwiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For in thoſe things wherein care and induſtry is of any force (among which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40523:7"/>
things ſorrow is one, as we have ſaid) we muſt obſerve, not whence the paſſion comes, but whither it goes. 'Tis the office of reaſon to look forward, not backward. Wherefore he that doth any thing ought often to put the queſtion to himſelf, Why do I do this? What do I hope? What do I deſire? This if one ask himſelf who cheriſheth his grief and endeavoureth not to correct it, he ſhall ſee how nothing can be anſwered.</p>
            <p>But you may object, It is hard and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane to expell out of your heart the thought of her you lov'd ſo dearly and ſo deſervedly, not leſs for her vertues, then becauſe ſhe was your wife. Remember, 'tis requir'd but for a time, and, as in a labyrinth, this way leads you to a place contrary unto it. So doth a ſhort absti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence conduce to the better concoction and digeſtion of the food you ſhall eat. I would have her live in your thoughts perpetually, but ſo that the memory of her may delight, not torment you. 'Tis an injury to her, when ſhe is called into your minde to create her husband ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. Let her come then, when ſhe may come, in the quality ſhe was wont to come, fair, kinde and cheerfull. This image of her, which now occurrs to your
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40523:7"/>
minde, ſorrowfull, and leaving a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome remembrance of her, is falſe and reſembles her not. I do now foreſee the time, when that ſweetneſs of manners, that love and reverence of you, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied care in the good education of her children, that ſincere piety toward God, and whatſoever in many of that ſex is wanting, in ſome few is moſt praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, will offer it ſelf to your minde, not only without danger, but with much ſenſe of joy: when it will delight you to remember her, and to ſet before your childrens eyes all her actions as the beſt Samplar for their life. Only for a little while put by the thought of her, which you ſhall afterward reſume with advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. To this end, as I was ſaying, will avail theſe many weighty affairs, which being enough to oppreſſe another, ſit lightly upon you. Now is the time, if ever, to be immerſed in publick cares, and ſuffer no room at all in the minde to be unpoſſeſt. Nor are the conferences of friends unprofitable, provided they be men of courage and wiſdom, not ſuch as commend themſelves by the imitation of your ſadneſſe. Conferre with the dead alſo, and turn over Books with greater diligence now then ever, and let that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40523:8"/>
which was but your recreation before, now become a part of your labour. Books will not only give you a ſafe retreat from the enemies fury, but arms alſo againſt the enemy. For whether you contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate with your moſt capacious ſoul the nature of things, you will ſee how no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is without the empire of death, no not the elements themſelves: It is the moſt univerſal law, which condemns e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing that is born, to dye; and it were great ignorance to think one perſon can be exempted from the common ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine: Or, whether you turn to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, among that fair company of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues you ſhall behold <hi>Fortitude,</hi> of a firm body, a head lifted up, a chearfull coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, but among the vices <hi>Sorrow,</hi> macilent, pale, of a cloudy brow, and down-caſt looks: Or, whether you ſearch the <hi>Animals,</hi> you ſhall finde examples of men, who have born the deaths of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Children, Wives, with a minde leſſe mov'd then ours is at the reading of the ſtory. Now, having by theſe Arts eſcaped the dangers of the firſt time, and withall gotten ſtrength, let the ſoul at length come forth into the field, as it were, and prepare to fight.</p>
            <p>But here alſo I think it fit to imitate
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40523:8"/>
wiſe Commanders, who, as much as they can, ſever the enemies forces, that fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the ſeverall parties, they may more eaſily conquer all. Mourning is a confuſed thing, it objects unto the minde many things at once and in a heap, which being joyned terrific, but vaniſh being divided. All the aſſaults it makes againſt you are either in reſpect of Her whom you lament, or of your ſelf the Mourner, or of your children, with whom and for whom you mourn. Weigh theſe particulars ſeverally, you will finde part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that there is no cauſe of grief, partly that the incommodity is much overba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanced by greater good. I will begin with Her. It is in all mens mouths, which we read every where in Chriſtian Writers, but in <hi>Antiphanes</hi> too (which you may more admire) a heathen Poet ſpeaking in words of this ſenſe:
<q>
                  <l>Lament your friends with ſorrow moderate:</l>
                  <l>They are not loſt, but gone before, where Fate</l>
                  <l>Diſpoſeth all: And we, in order, muſt</l>
                  <l>One after one be turn'd to the ſame duſt;</l>
                  <l>And meet at the ſame Inn by ſeveral waies,</l>
                  <l>And in another world ſhall ſee new daies.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>We muſt dwell the longer upon this place, becauſe it alone without the reſt, if it be rightly conſidered, is ſufficient for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40523:9"/>
conſolation. I would not have any credit given me without a moſt competent wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the Doctor of the Gentiles, the Founder of Churches, called to be an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle by a voice from heaven; who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indued alſo with humane learning, all other arguments omitted, checks the immodeſty of ſorrow with this alone: I would not have you ignorant, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, concerning them that are aſleep, that ye ſorrow not even as others which have no hope. For if we beleeve that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus died and roſe again, even ſo them that are aſleep will God bring with him. It is the manner of Epiſtles to deliver in ſhort that which familiar diſcourſe doth expreſſe more liberally. But if <hi>Paul,</hi> as it is beleeved, after he wrote this, viſited his Diſciples of <hi>Macedon</hi> again, he might haply proſecute this moſt wholeſome point more at large after this ſort: Freinds, whom nature hath made of the ſame kinde with us, and the Word of God hath new made and raiſed to the ſame Grace; ye know it is our duty throughly to purge out whatſoever old corruption remaineth in you; your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, your habit and geſture ſpeak you to be much and long grieved in minde, it any of your deareſt Relatives be taken
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40523:9"/>
out of your ſight. Nor is it any marvel, for thus did your fathers, and thus do the people with whom you live intermixed: Great is the power of a vice commended by the authority of parents, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes which have ſeized, not upon ſingle perſons, but whole Nations, are very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious: but you muſt remember to what Inſtitution you have given your name: in your baptiſm, when the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of your body figured the cleanneſſe of minde, I received your vow to forſake the world. Peace with God is not bought at any cheaper rate. We have doctrines, we have alſo rites which ſeparate us from the world, and make us a people different from all the reſt of mankinde: Even our words are not the ſame, whom they call dead, we ſay are fallen aſleep: So are we taught to ſpeak by him that is not only the Maſter of life but ſpeech. What is the meaning of that new word? That ſleep is the image of death, even the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets of the Grecians and their Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers have delivered; but with them the ſimilitude holds not, which with us is moſt exact. By motion and action we underſtand life: there is a defect of theſe, when the body is tied up with the bonds of ſleep, and lies as it were buried: when
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40523:10"/>
the morning Sun hath driven away the night, that vigour that was not loſt but intermitted returns again: mean while, the ſoul which hath a power not depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the body, performing the offices of both times, perpetuates her action; So when the term of mortall life is come, the body lies torpid and unactive, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it retain as yet the ſhape it had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly before, or elſe hath rendred its parts to the original duſt. But wait un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the great day ſhine forth, there it will appear, the body reſted for a time which ſeemed loſt. In the mean, that part which is inviſible keeps poſſeſſion of life in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the whole man. Compare with this our faith, what others running into ſo many by-waies do conceive: when in very many and the greateſt things their opinions differ, in this almoſt alone they agree, that they are without hope of life ever to return unto the body, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deprive man of his immortality. For man is a body animate, not a ſoul with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a body, nor a body without a ſoul. The ſoul it ſelf departed from the body, many of them either think to be annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, or at leaſt not to retain the ſtate of its own ſubſtance. So the whole man, to them, is deſtroyed without hope of reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40523:10"/>
as appears by thoſe very conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which they apply to mourners. For they ſay, Dead men indeed have no good; but neither have they any ill. Now, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the opinion of theſe men is hard, yet theirs is much harder who make the ſoul outlive the body. For that lower place which they will have to be the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſeat of ſouls gone out of the body, they deſcribe as a wilde place, horrid and dark, and of ſuch a condition, that one would die another death to get out of it. Moreover, which is worſt of all, They to whom other puniſhments are remitted are (according to this opinion) ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly under this torment, a vain and never ſatisfied deſire of returning back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to their former life. If ſome few a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe men have any better conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, they doubt and fluctuate more like to thoſe that wiſh then affirm. But ye have learned among the elements of our doctrine, that life remains in the ſoul, and ſhall be reſtored to the body. That which is the conſummation of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, concludes the <hi>formula</hi> in our holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itiation. For being asked whether ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved the Reſurrection of the body, and the life everlaſting, ye anſwered every one before God and his Chuach, that ye did
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40523:11"/>
beleeve. Upon this <hi>formula</hi> the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that you made I now treat with you: but it is not ſufficient to give a light aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that perſwaſion muſt be firmly root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in your mindes, ſo ſhall it bring forth mature and fair and laſting fruits. Much will avail to this purpoſe, the attent me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of thoſe Arguments by which you were induced to ſubſcribe to this Faith. We caught you not by the affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ornaments of humane eloquence, nor did we by a long chain of conſequences entangle the mindes of the more igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; but we brought the buſineſſe to that which is common to men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, learned and unlearned, young and old, and which is accounted the greateſt aſſurance of all, even to the judgement of ſenſe. The moſt famous enquirer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to nature among the Grecians, gives this reaſon why we have not the knowledge of many things; becauſe we can neither ſee them with our eyes, nor touch them with our hands: by which way things are wont to come unto the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. God hath excluded us from this excuſe and pretence for our ignorance. He hath preſented to our hands and eyes a <hi>ſpecimen</hi> and pledge of what we hope for. That Jeſus Chriſt the Authour of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40523:11"/>
our faith was nailed to the croſſe, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Croſſe, all <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſaw, the Senate ſaw, the Roman band ſaw it with their eyes, and alſo that multitude of ſtrangers wherewith that great City was then filled: That he was buried and lay in the Sepulcher two whole nights, and the day interpoſed, is manifeſt, both by the declaration of the Seal, and by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the watch. So far we and our adverſaries are agreed. This ſame Jeſus after that time women ſaw living again, his followers alſo ſaw him, both ſeverally and all the eleven together, at divers times: There were ſome alſo that hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his hands and ſide. That nothing might be wanting to make faith com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, He ſhewed himſelf to be ſeen and heard by five hundred witneſſes at once: who in good part are living and do teſtifie the ſame. To come unto my ſelf, I have ſeen Him ſhining with divine Majeſty, and by his immediate authority was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and vowed to be his ſervant whom before I had perſecuted. And can any one yet be doubtfull? Certainly, never did any equall Judge reject ſo many wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, men of integrity, and ſuch as had no temptation to make a lye. This teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is ſo farre from being gainfull to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40523:12"/>
us, that we muſt pay for it with the loſſe of all things, for the ſaving whereof lyes are wont to be invented. Therefore doe we incurre the hatred even of our neareſt Relatives; we are diſpoſſeſt of our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, we are baniſht from our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, we are in hazard of our life every day. No man at ſo dear a price doth buy the pleaſure of deceiving another. Now if our teſtimony be received by amoſt evident example it is manifeſt that God can reſtore life to a dead body, And by the ſame Argument it is evinced, that this ſhall be done for all the Diſciples of Chriſts inſtitution, if that be certain, which was certainly heard by many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, that Chriſt hath promiſed it. For the Reſurrection of our bodies is aſſured by Chriſts teſtimony, the veracity of Chriſt is witneſſed by his Reſurrection. Neither could it ſtand with the equity of God to give that honour to one that ſpake not the truth, eſpecially when him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf before the event had ſet it for a ſign: Wherefore beleeve us, that Chriſt is ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen; and beleeve Chriſt, that all ſhall riſe to immortall bleſſedneſſe and bleſſed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality who die his Diſciples. He ſhall preſent us to the Father, who hath once obtained ſuch grace with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40523:12"/>
that no requeſt of his can ever be in vain: He ſhall make us partakers of his glory, and bring us into thoſe places, where dwels an undiſturbed peace; where neither diſeaſes ſhall approach the body, nor vices have acceſſe unto the minde; where ſhall be life without fear of death, and joys without mixture of ſorrow. Some taſte of this ſupper have the ſouls already, that are departed hence in the faith of Chriſt, in moſt ſweet tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity waiting for the conſummati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their felicity, together with the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. He that heartily beleeves theſe things, muſt needs be ſo far from lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he will congratulate their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py condition, whom he hath ſent away before him to the enjoyment of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon hopes. For in a true judgement they are not dead, but freed now at laſt from their mortality. This place of <hi>Paul</hi> hath carried me farther then I intended, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt I endeavour to examine every one of his words, and the force of them. For I am aſſured, there can be no better reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy applied to ſorrow, then that which the great Phyſician of ſouls among the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite treaſures of ſaving wiſedome hath brought down from Heaven. And yet, how many things have I omitted, which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40523:13"/>
might be drawn from the fame fountain? But thoſe conſiderations that we have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced thence, if they be taken to heart, and received throughly, will be ſufficient. Beleeve it, excellent Sir, as if you ſaw it, the ſoul of your wife for many reaſons moſt beloved, begins already to enjoy the ſweet fruits of her virtues, and taſteth the rewards promiſed to ſincere piety. The end and conſummation of ſo many ages, when ſhe ſhall be wholly reſtored to her ſelf; that immenſe accumulation of all good things, to which all that can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined is far inferiour, is not expected afar off, as by us; but lookt upon by her at the neareſt diſtance. What ſhe hath in poſſeſſion is ſo great, that ſhe wanteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; and yet that is more which ſhe ſeeth ſhe ſhall poſſeſſe. Nor have you any reaſon to ſay, She might have ſtayed lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger before ſhe went thither. Time is ſome advantage, and it is a great felicity to be quickly happy. How many evils, partly certain, partly uncertain, doth he eſcape who is called hence betimes? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are the examples of men that have paid dear for the lengthening of their life? I might here relate the torments of diſeaſes, and the affronts of fortune never more to be feared then when ſhe flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40523:13"/>
and the incommodities of old age which every man that lives long ſhall be ſure of. This one thing ſeemeth to me a ſufficient benefit of an early death, to be put out of danger of ſinning any more. It remains that you ſay, I am not ſorry for her ſake, but my own: And to this I was now coming, for that is wont to be ſaid; but how unjuſtly, any one may eaſily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand whoſe ejulations have not made him deaf to the voice of reaſon. He that flyes to this refuge manifeſtly ſhews him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf an offender againſt the laws of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. For they that fetcht the originall of friendſhip from indigence, were enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with the hiſſes of almoſt all Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers; nor among the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whoſe manner is to meaſure moſt things by profit, could they make good their cauſe. In friendſhip, the Affection goes abroad, and without ſelf-reſpect, ſeeks the good of another. Applauſes fill the Theater, as oft as any <hi>Pilades</hi> derives upon himſelf the dangers of <hi>Oreſtes:</hi> ſo prone is the conſent of men to eſteem it the office of a friend, in an equall matter to prefer his friends ſafety before his own. How much more ought the ſenſe of our own incommodity and loſſe be ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up by the felicity of one we profeſſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40523:14"/>
to love; when we conſider here is much more of good then there of evill. <hi>Zopyrus</hi> is commended in the ſtory, becauſe he cut and diſmembred his own body, to the end his King might obtain a great, yet but one City. In this caſe there was ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon: but in yours, if in the one ſcale you put your wife advanced to the very gates of Eternity, enjoying the ſociety of Chriſt and the bleſſed ſouls, free from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing that may occaſion either grief or fear; in the other ſcale place your ſelf, deſtitute of thoſe commodities which a happy matrimony prolonged for ſome more years might adde unto you, there will be found no weight in your part of the balance, the beam will not ſtand at all, but ſpeedily turn with the great weight on the other ſide, as if on yours were nothing. What if I acquit you from this compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and convince you that your incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities weighed by themſelves are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing really, but only in opinion? For wherein, is he more unhappy who hath loſt a wife, then he who never had one? In opinion there is ſome difference, for the memory of the thing once poſſeſſed repreſents the image, the image excites the deſire: but this is the judgement of the lower bench, we may appeal. Let your
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40523:14"/>
Reaſon aided by ſo much experience, and inſtructed by ſo much reading, ſit in the Judgement-ſeat and pronounce the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. That which is paſt, is not; and therefore can have no efficiency: nothing is ours but whileſt we have it; afterward it pertains no more unto us, then that which is fartheſt from us. Really then, He that never had, and he that now hath not, are in the like caſe; but that he ſeems the more ingratefull, who from the benefit he once enjoyed takes an occaſion to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain. Would you therefore ſee, how not miſerable you are? Look upon ſo many thouſands of men, who to their laſt years have willingly and by their own choiſe lived a ſingle life: in which number are many learned men, pious, prudent, and ſuch as were not ignorant either of the good or evill wherewith married men are attended. Wives are helps and comforts to their husbands: but they muſt be likewiſe helped and comforted. And if the burden be equally divided, there is no more in one whole burden, then in half of that which is double to it. Such is the nature of the contract, that it laies the harder bond upon the men, to whoſe protection the infirmer ſex commends it ſelf. One in the Greek Comedy, if God ſhould
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40523:15"/>
offer him a double body, ſaith he would refuſe the favour; his reaſon is, becauſe with multiplicity of the parts his care would be multiplied. It is indeed a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant thing in proſperity to have one to whom you may do good: but the more favourably fortune fils your ſails, the more you muſt contract them, and take heed leſt even in the greateſt innocence your behaviour give colour and occaſion unto Calumny, which doth cloſely purſue men of higher fortunes. If any adverſity befall you, it is true the wife partakes of the ſorrow, but it returns and lies hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vier upon the husband: as the rayes of the Sun reflected from the ground do the more inflame the air. The Grief de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from a dear perſon whom you behold grieving for you, is more grievous then the primitive. I alledge not theſe things as if I had undertaken the <hi>Encomium</hi> of a ſingle life: it is enough for me to ſhew, that ſeeing either life hath its commodities tempered and mixt with the incommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, it becomes every one, with an equall and indifferent minde, to conform him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to that lot and condition that hath befallen him. The laſt pretence of grief is the moſt ſpecious, in reſpect of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren whoſe education, when the care is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40523:15"/>
divided between the two parents, proceeds the better. This is ſomewhat, but herein hath God abundantly provided for you. You are a man of unwearied vigour; and if you pleaſe to uſe your whole ſtrength, able to ſupply the place of both ſexes: Cut off from your buſineſſes and ſtudies ſo much as that charge requires, yea, think that charge to be the beſt ſtudy and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Matters of moſt conſequence exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute your ſelf, the leſſer commit to others: and as oft as you can, viſit your ſweet children with your paternall eye, now alſo ſerving for the maternall. And look upon the great ſupporters of your Houſe, your moſt gracious King, by whom your dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and truſt are well tried, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore well eſteemed; Your honourable em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, your eſtate vertuouſly acquired, your kindred, alliance, friends, flouriſhing and proſperous. You ſee if any acceſſion ſhall be made unto your labour, how great comforts are given you aforehand. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, that very labour will decreaſe under your hand, whenas every one of your children ſhall ripen in years, ſo he will ſucceed into the care both of himſelf and the reſt. But how little of juſtice there is in your complaint of this burthen, you may even hereby underſtand. Had your
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40523:16"/>
Wife left you a houſe empty of children, I beleeve as the cuſtome is, you would ſay,
<q>
                  <l>O hadſt thou left ſome might me father call,</l>
                  <l>O for one childe to play about my Hall!</l>
               </q>
But had ſome Prophet, foretold before your marriage day, You ſhall, for many years have a happy and peaceable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of your wife, only you know one of you muſt needs outlive the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: this indulgence ſhall be yielded to the more tender ſex, that ſhe may not mourn for you. Chooſe whether you pleaſe, by her and after her to be called Father, or no. You would have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, I doubt not, Let me have, when I can have her no longer, O let me have ſome living images of her, and ſucceſſors of our common fortunes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Riches then unhappy are,</l>
               <l>When they do not finde an heir.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Well then, what is it that compels you, or I may ſay, permits you to grieve? Your wife? But ſhe is bleſſed. A wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowers ſtate which is impoſed on you? The ſingle life hath adventured at all times to compare it ſelf with wedlock, in point of felicity. Children? You would not be without them; if you
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40523:16"/>
were childleſſe, you would be more ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull. And do you now grieve be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are not childleſſe? It is great moroſity, to accuſe and complain of every fortune. But if this diſcourſe may ſeem too rigid and ſevere, I will be a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more remiſſe, and grant that ſome adverſity is befallen you; yet will I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by evince, that you have reaſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce. That the power and the wiſdom of God are unlimited, we do all acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Hence it follows, nothing can happen without his knowledge who is omniſcient, without his permiſſion who is omnipotent. Whatſoever he either doth or permitteth, he hath good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it. God hath care of all things, but not equally, becauſe they are not equall. According to the ſeverall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of things, there be degrees of Providence. He governs with a more carefull hand the affairs of men, then of inferiour creatures. And among all mankinde, he hath a nearer inſpection over Kings, and other Rulers of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, who are, as it were, earthly ſtars, from whoſe influence either the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts of warre, or the calms of peace deſcend upon the people. But above all, moſt dear unto that ſupream Goodneſſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40523:17"/>
are faithfull Chriſtians. The divine pleaſure is, that Kingdoms themſelves ſhould be ſerviceable to them: and in all conſtitutions through the whole world, they are favoured with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular reſpect. Therefore, even thoſe things are for them, which ſeem againſt them: according to that immutable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, <hi>All things fall out for the beſt to thoſe that purely worſhip God.</hi> Nor may we wonder, if God keeps them not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licately but under diſcipline. This is a fathers part. Either they muſt be purged by ſome ſharp and nimble medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, if they have contracted any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion from the multitude with whom they converſe; or, before the diſeaſe take hold upon them, the ſouls health muſt be preſerved by ſome wholſome, though bitter, potion; or elſe, the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier of God is to be proved by encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring with an enemy, that himſelf may perceive, and others may not be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant what a proficient he is. Matters of difficulty are provided for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe and illuſtration of every vertue. God hath alwaies ſet godly men to ſuch a task: but he juſtly exacteth more from Chriſtian men, who by the very enſign of the Croſs are given to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40523:17"/>
upon what terms they are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into ſervice. The chief Captain himſelf having made his way to heaven by patience, and ſtruggled through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſufferings, hath conſecrated the ſame way for us. The ſouldier that is not called forth into any danger, may fear, his Commander holds him in ſmall eſteem. And who would not couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly deſcend into that combate, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is a certain reward for him that conquers, and certain conqueſt for him that fights? For he that is the Rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, is alſo a Helper, he ſhews the crown, he ſupplieth arms. Nor need we excuſe our ſelves by pretence of weakneſſe. The moſt equal Arbiter and Judge of the field, doth ſo fitly match every combatant, that he calleth forth none to fight, but whom he knows able or will make ſo. He can no more deny his heavenly aid to the man that praies aright, then a loving and wealthy father can deny bread to his ſon, that asketh it when he is hungry. How many of the old Philoſophers, how many alſo of a lower rank, having but ordinary encouragements and ſupports, have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued Sorrow? and ſhall we, who are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſtitute of the uſe of reaſon, nor of the ſuccours of good learning, and beſides
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40523:18"/>
are aſſured of that excellent and peculiar aid from heaven, turn our back and yield to any calamity how great ſoever? That can become no man, and you leaſt of all, moſt honoured Sir, you are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to an eminent place, where you ſhine both by your own light, and by that which you borrow from the Majeſty of your King. Whatſoever you do is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, and goes into example. Let it be hereafter ſaid; Bear your wifes death as <hi>Maurier</hi> did. Nor may you fear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuſpected for to have loved your wife leſſe, if you mourn leſſe. Keep her vertues in your memory, deliver them to your children, and as you can by ingenuous and glorious monuments propagate them to poſterity. Theſe are truer Tokens of your love, then to do what ſhe would not have you. Among all nations the Wills of the deceaſed are ſacred and inviolate, and not only ſuch as are declared in word, or committed to writing, but alſo if by probable arguments we can conjecture what their wills were. You are not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant what her will was, and what ſhe deſires now, if in that place of reſt there be any care of our affairs; to wit, that you may paſs the remainder of your life with greateſt felicity, and never think on
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40523:18"/>
her but with a quiet, and (if it may be) a joyfull minde. The ſame you muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be the Kings pleaſure, whom it concerns, that both in body and minde you may be ſtrong and healthy. To add any more might ſeem to proceed from a diffidence of your wiſdom and courage. What I have ſaid, how much better could you ſay to your ſelf? and ſo, I hope, you nave done. It would be a joy to me to have performed my duty, and that you needed it not. Nor will it be unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to you, to be aſſured of your friends fidelity by the ſuccours offered, although your victory atchieved, ſooner then was hoped, hath made them of no uſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Lupiſten,</hi> 
                  <date>11 <hi>Calend.</hi> Mar. <hi>An.</hi> 1621.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
